for decades surfers have traveled the
world in search of the perfect wave now
for the first time in history we may
actually be on the verge of creating
that perfect wave thanks to the South
Bay chapter of the Surfrider Foundation
and Chevron USA it will not be the first
surfing Beach to have been created by
man engineering projects that were
directed towards other goals such as the
construction of peers and jetties have
created some fine brakes like by
accident but never before has a project
been undertaken whose basic purpose was
to create ocean surf applying the kind
of expertise that has traditionally been
lavished on industry the designers of
the El Segundo reef hoped to restore
some portion of what has been lost
through coastal development and to
preserve one of the great pleasures the
beaches of the world afford us some see
it as the beginning of a new chapter in
environmental engineering a whole new
way of thinking about the oceans and how
we ought to treat them the winter of
1983 marked one of the strongest El Nino
events in the last century the violent
winter storms caused widespread damage
throughout Southern California but it's
brunt was felt along the coast where
heavy surf magnified by unusually high
tides pounded oceanfront communities
with waves up to 15 feet the unrelenting
surf battered the coast for weeks when
it was all over the waves had caused
extensive erosion along the coast and
left Chevron's El Segundo marine
terminal and pipelines without a
protective Beach
in response to the erosion chevron
proposed installing a 900 foot rock
jetty with a renourishment project to
fill the area surrounding the jetty with
approximately six hundred and twenty
thousand cubic feet of sand local
surfers hope that the installation of
the jetty would create a new break and
at first it appeared they gotten their
wish but later developments proved
otherwise
surfing photographer Mike falls are
observed the construction of the jetty
and witnessed the early reaction of the
surfing community
I started shooting it right when they
started constructing the jetty when they
they first started putting the initial
rocks out and then they put a crane up
on those rocks and then the crane would
bring in at more rocks in front of it
and slowly worked its way out so I did
start shooting it when they started to
construct that and at the same time they
were they were bringing sand on the
beach some of the sand came from the
excavation over Hyperion and they put it
on conveyor belts and a conveyor belt
into the area and then bulldozers pushed
it out from where the bike path was
pushed at West wheeler or towards the
ocean and made along the beach after
1984 once the jetty was built a lot of
people in this area had a lot of high
hopes that it would actually create some
sort of a surf spot the biggest standout
guys from this area at the time would
have been Ted Robinson Nick Christianson
Kelly Gibson and Chris Roja and they
were beginning to surf that area quite a
bit in an area just just north of the
jetty because it was away from the the
main scene where everyone could drive
into the parking lot now Porto and see
the good waves they were heading to this
spot no one really knew about it it was
kind of their own little secret spot
in the early 1980s
Ted Nick Kelly and Chris were selected
to be on the National scholastic Surfing
associations national team the
experience of competing on an
international level gave them the
confidence to tackle the expert only
waves the new jetty created over the
first day that we could surf it me and
Ted surf didn't like to claim we were
the first guys out there it was first
put in it was a little bit longer
probably bout a hundred yards longer I
don't think Kelly's accurate when he
said he surfed at first I thought I was
out there about two weeks before he went
it was a I think that the best thing
about that jetty is that it wasn't on
the search box camera because of how
beat up they were get how hard the way
broke in really shallow water and
they're basically every time they go out
they say they just got hammered when
they were out there
we shot really for the first time at the
El Segundo jetty and it was Ted Robinson
crisp Roja and kind of a cast of a local
guy so I was just gentleman up in the
air on Ted come on get down there you
know I wanted to get him out in the
water as soon as possible but try to get
you know the really good light well you
know I just wanted him out water and I
didn't really have a care about how
heartless paddle out or anything like
that you know a lot of people get the
wrong perspective at that place because
it's maybe one in ten or fifteen waves
that are like that so you know it's it's
made out to be a premier surf spot and
it really
I mean it it has its days maybe two
three times a year four times and it's
maybe only one out of every 15 ways that
are good like that so it's I mean it's
kind of a fake and in that sense I mean
quality of the waves have been affected
in a negative way and I as far as I am
concerned back when before that jetty
was put in it used to be better what
happened was you know just storm surge
the rocks ended up getting shifted
around and then shortened the jetties
behind it looks like it's probably at
least cut in half for my originals
it's not what it was you can't really
surf the right and the left on the north
side is a real random way but it breaks
him the best year maybe three to five
pounds a year the new wave broke three
to five times a year and only the most
experienced surfers could ride it the
damage from the project was extreme but
was lost for the average surfer was a
half-mile stretch of beach that once had
consistently fine waves all year long
the Surfrider Foundation is a grassroots
environmental organization dedicated to
the protection and enhancement of the
worlds waves and beaches members are
powerful spokespeople and caretakers of
the ocean environment Chris Jones Tom
Marcelino and Rick page are the driving
force of the South Bay chapter beach
erosion was a problems with Chevron in
the refinery here right in El Segundo
the jetty that exists now was built to
protect the beach and prevent beach
erosion
torching one of the side effects was it
had a detrimental effect on the existing
surfer by putting the jetty there
they've managed to stop with sand flow
there is thickened the beach on 14 by
doing that you changed the way the wave
breaks over the the current reef and
sandbars that are normally built up by
storm work and and wave action all the
time so wherever there's a jetty you end
up getting one little peak maybe out of
it but you destroy the natural beach
break that normally would exist on the
South Bay chapter of Surfrider initiated
some discussions with Chevron to
determine what could be done to address
the fact that the jetty had diminished
surf in the area I started the Surfrider
Foundation in 1984 one of the very first
things I did and getting that
organization off the ground was become a
team create a team of guys who I thought
knew a lot about surfing Lance Carson
Chris Blakely dan young and most
importantly Tom Pratt
Tom Pratt was the first professional
environmentalist who was also a surfer
Tom Pratt had done a survey to determine
the effects that Chevron jetty had had
on the area he was looking for local
surfers that had anecdotal experience
and he was basically putting together
his report on the effect of the jetty on
surf in that area which later was
completed and presented to the
California Coastal Commission
ten years ago I was before this
commission when the surfing community
secured a condition regarding this
chevron project at El Segundo that would
provide mitigation if surfing conditions
were adversely impacted by the project
at the time Chevron agreed to this
permit condition they predicted their
experts predicted that the surfing
conditions would be as good or better
than they than the existing conditions
they agreed to the condition requiring
the surf monitoring and the potential
mitigation it's been found that it's
documented that there have been adverse
impacts that are significant to surfing
attributable to this project the
represented surfing community which was
which I have a lot of personal respect
and because I've got to know a lot of
them over the last number of years would
have you believe that the only
acceptable mitigation is some kind of
replacement of the resource they've used
Chevron is solely responsible for this
issue and have been unwilling to accept
suggestions there are a lot of other
issues to play here that problem has
been compounded by the fact that we've
had a lot of different personalities
change during the course of the
discussion over the last seven years my
concern is that they want to use this as
an example and I think in in proprietary
it is a feeling the Surfrider Foundation
and the people of the surface of the
community that the only true mitigation
is restoration of the surf
we are not anti-business we are pro
Chevron we think Chevron has done an
outstanding job to this date but we feel
much more is needed we must have
restoration of the way the technology is
here it's as if I were driving my car I
get hit by another driver and I make my
claim against the other driver and they
go I'm not gonna give you your car and
I'm not gonna give you money back to buy
another car gonna give you this book
that says best car is to get hit by and
then you can just keep on waiting till
you get hit by the right car and then
that car has to replace it and
mitigation to do studies and to remove a
rock or two certainly doesn't replace
beaches and certainly doesn't replace
surfing opportunities that have been
lost what I'm here in the Surfrider say
is hey we've lost surfing conditions and
Beach big bad developer we don't want
studies studies doesn't give us more
surfing area we want surfing area
I think the locals who surf you realize
that and they had known for many years
that the surf had changed and was
diminished because of the construction
of the jetty Rick pages our Chevron
liaison and at that time he joined with
Tom Pratt and really took the lead and
hammered home Surfrider's fervent desire
to address this issue this is our
backyard this is a piece of the coast
that we're responsible for and it's not
something we were going to let go by now
the key player in the whole negotiation
the whole game has been
Tom Pratt was a surfer from Englewood
area and Tom was the original founder of
the Surfrider Foundation it's probably
the first surf eco where and when this
project came out Tom had been put into
the permit that if the surf were damaged
there'd be some restoration involved or
mitigation with the exact room through
the efforts of Surfrider the Chevron
organization was forced to come up with
money for the mitigation of the surf
zone harif came about we were trying to
decide what is what is appropriate
mitigation mitigation means replacement
or repairing of something that's been
destroyed the reef technology can
accomplish two things number one we have
a sand erosion problem in the South Bay
these are not natural beaches yes
surfing reef is basically an underwater
breakwater there for a week and maybe
solve two problems we can create waves
and protect the beach because if we
don't protect the beach we're gonna have
to do these speech nourishment projects
anyway so this may be killing two birds
with one stone and everybody's happy
might be a win-win situation we settled
on Dave Skelly engineering the reason we
set out settled on day one is he was
very enthusiastic about project most
important is that Dave addressed the
concern that was foremost in my mind
would building this reef destroy
something there'd be also done the
locals value then that was Dave's the
thrust of his whole project he shares
what we can do without hurting something
else Scali engineering was selected by
the Surfrider Foundation to design
engineer and permit the first artificial
surfing reef as part of a condition of
compliance but on the Chevron
Corporation for some of the work they
did back in 1982 and 83 right here on
this beach and my company specializes
just in coastal projects such as harbors
marina sea walls jetties groins and
breakwaters that's what this project is
it's actually a submerged breakwater
this project is kind of the dream of
every surfer
I know somebody that's been surfing for
30 years I am myself that thought a lot
about this and I'm really looking
forward to the opportunity to do this
it's we've come up with a real simple
design and we basically just want to
prove the concept we want to prove that
we can go out there and make waves break
in such a way that they're more surfable
and I think that you know in the future
we'll probably see more exotic type
projects but this is the first step and
this is a big step - for for surfing in
general many surfers have dreamed of
building a reef to create a perfect wave
one such surfer was the late great hoppy
Schwartz the father of organized surfing
hobbies best friend photographer Leroy
Grannis documented the building of this
reef perhaps the first attempt to create
surfable waves by modifying the ocean
floor attempt to build a reef took place
in april of 71 and it was about two
blocks north of the Redondo breakwater
and approximately an hundred yards off
the beach the original idea was to
funnel surf over this reef to make it
break in the perfect shape and spread
out and have a good shoulder on it Phil
and Merlin Olsen a couple of round
football players in the offseason had a
business going they called erosion
control West which beefed up properties
along the oceanfront that were
threatened by high tides and the storm
served in that kind of thing
this is phil olson with a the bags what
they did was take his pump sucks and off
at the bottom and blow it into these
bags here until they got filled up Hoffs
idea was to build a be shaped reef up
off the bottom of the sand with each
sandbags the idea was real good the only
problem was that after it got built with
the constant wave action it finally
settled flare into the sand and
disappeared
although no waves ever broke on Hoppy's
reef the original concept was ahead of
its time one of the myths about this
project is that it's a it's really a
complex engineering problem the reality
is though that the environment out there
is so complex and ever-changing that the
engineering is quite simple the biggest
hurdle for this project is actually
getting permission to do it and that's
the permitting phase I have to deal with
agencies on the city level the state
level and the federal level which makes
it rather a lot of Hoops to jump through
we know through from previous studies
this about amount of material we needed
to put out there and we know the amount
of money so that kind of dictated the
design and what I drew on is from some
using geo textile fabrics and it's a
application that's been used in other
environments primarily river
environments so what I did is I've taken
existing technology and applied it in a
unique way so my concept is to put out
gigantic sand bags a nice bag weighs
about 12 to 14 tons that's a rather
large bag geotextile bags have been used
on the Mississippi River to control bank
erosion they've also been used on the
East Coast for coastal structures such
as groins and dikes for dredge spoils
containment the interesting thing is
that these bags will last probably at
least two decades and possibly longer
construction in the surf zone is really
difficult and out here at El Segundo we
have a 10-foot tide range a mobile
bottom and waves that come from
different directions that the formation
that we're placing these bags in is a
chevron shape formation or v-shaped and
hopefully that will create a good right
break and a good left break well because
we're going to put a bump out there
we're hoping to make a plunging way kind
of a wave with a little bit of attitude
something that's a little different than
you see out here more of the gentle
rolling wave again the wave field is so
complex here it's going to be hard to
make any kind of certain way because the
waves change the wave height the wave
period in the wave direction
changes on a daily basis but we are
locating the reef in deeper water so
that nobody can hit it so waves this
break directly on the reef will probably
be six to eight foot in height now in
the Lee of the reef a sandbar will form
and smaller breakers will break on that
sandbar probably more of a collapsing
wave or a spilling wave instead of the
classic plunging wave like you see it to
say the Banzai Pipeline one of the
problems I had with this wreath is I'm
not an El Segundo local that's not mine
brakes and I we had to talk extensively
the El Segundo people because it's their
backyard and not ours
but as soon as the chapter the South Bay
chapter was involved I thought that my
duty was to represent the El Segundo
people and no one else the last thing I
would want to do is interrupt any kind
of existing surf club the this reef is
going to be limited to maybe 100 to 200
feet on either side of it in the max
this is based on several things it's
based on experience it's based on
scientific evidence is based on what we
know about this shoreline there really
is a science to making surf spots we did
some real extensive talking both before
and after this agreement was made with
the elders on the locals after we made
the agreement with Chevron I still went
back to Tyler Hezekiah's Kurt's shape
for some of the some of the people who
are there we've been there all their
life to find out if we were gonna shove
something down to throw it they didn't
want it's very important that they get
what they want or don't do anything if
that's what they wish they also go no we
have
and we have the pipe one of my major
concerns is location and how it would
affect the spots surrounding like that
reef would be put I think there's a
great future for surfing reefs I think
the big companies getting behind
something like that would be great as
long as the surfers agreed with them
being the first project of its kind
there's a lot of people watching this
and I think we have to kind of
understand what this whole project is
about so we can measure the success I
think that in a sense this projects
already successful because we've
established a surf break as a valuable
resource and we have a we're partnering
with a corporation to actually recreate
a surf break you know we have to be
realistic we're not in Hawaii we're not
in an area that has great waves in the
first place this has el segundo have
some good surfing spots but in general
it's it's not a world-class surfing area
so what we're gonna try to do is
basically prove the concept that we can
go out there and create a surfable wave
I believe that any kind of reefs that
they can do there's so much untapped
surf that would be really good do I
think it would be a good idea to build
more reefs yes I do do I think that this
was a great opportunity no question the
fact that they're gonna build an
artificial reef for surfing I think it
could only help I I'm excited about it
it's it's a great idea I would like to
be the first one house there to go try
it out when it's built you know it's a
piece of history
surfing is behind the times a little bit
you look at sports like skiing and we
can go out and make a ski slope here and
there and and other sports where they
can actually fill the need but here in
Southern California we have many many
more surfers than we have room for and
so I see a big future for creating surf
spots ultimately I see us taking large
objects and mooring them out in the surf
zone and using those objects to create
surf breaks I just envision something
like a skateboard park where they go out
mold the land to how they want escape we
can go out mold the land and then cast
it bring that structure outward in the
surf zone and create any kind of breaker
that we want it's it's the future people
have to remember that this is the start
of the 21st century of surfing you know
not the end this is just the first step
in many steps on creating good surf
spots for the future
I know a lot of these guys won't know
what finally placed that reef there but
for certain people that they probably
have anything should be remembered Tom
Pratt's probably the main person Tom
basically held AOL company accountable
for the destruction of a wave man was
definitely head of his time was a
visionary the whole project really is is
because of his foresight Tom passed away
of cancer shortly before this agreement
was made he did know that we were close
and that we probably would wrap it up
shortly
he got prostate cancer and passed away
six months after being being diagnosed
god bless him one mission it's Tom's
fight we could all pass a lot of credit
around it's time it's Tom's reef period
if we as surfers want to have any kind
of significant say and what's going on
in the beaches we're gonna have to have
some tangible victories we're gonna have
to say we started something here and
we're gonna defend it Chevron is a large
corporation and I feel personally that
there are probably other companies that
even though we had fought them tooth and
nail for years they may not have
acquiesced and so I think it's a feather
and Chevron's cap that I know some of
their corny commercials talk about you
know who cares people do and Chevron but
what they did they came through in this
case and I think they were weary at
first but I think they realized what had
happened and when the facts are
presented the right decision was made I
applaud their efforts on this titute the
important thing here is not the reef
though please don't think that the reef
is the issue it's not the issue is that
surfing that breaks will no longer be
destroyed because the Coastal Commission
has on record that surfing reef surfing
habitat is their wording is they worship
is a resource worthy of protection like
a tide land like a beach and that is the
key to the whole thing and the reef is
frosting on the cake it's something that
we can do it's going to be the first
step in surfing reef technology and an
object one to see what happens whether
the crest of the perfect wave will ever
rise from the waters off El Segundo
remains to be seen what is more
significant perhaps is the change in
thinking the project represents the
Prats reef project could pave the way
for other kinds of coastal restoration
it could lead to an era in which coastal
development is more responsible to the
diverse communities who use and
appreciate the ocean as an alternative
to unsightly jetties and groins under
water reefs could be used to preserve
sand beaches man-made reefs could also
serve as protective habitat for sea life
in short the world's engineers private
and public could begin to apply their
skills to the preservation and
restoration of precious ocean resources
rather than to their destruction
this wave comprised not of salt water
but of new ideas might be more
significant in the law
run than the surfers perfect wave
you